Finding Aid for Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam records and sound recordings, 1965-1966
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam records and sound recordings 1965-1966
Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam (1965: Ann Arbor, Mich.)
15 sound tape reels
0.5 linear feet
851510 Bimu C8 2
An international conference on Alternative Perspectives on Vietnam held at the University of Michigan, Sept. 14-18, 1965. Correspondence, minutes, clippings, printed materials, and sound recordings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of these records and tapes came from Rev. J. Edgar Edwards of Guild House (donor no. 4537 ) in 1967. A smaller portion came from Rev. Daniel Burke of Canterbury House (donor no. 4420 ) in 1966.
The record group is open to research.
The International Conference on Alternative Perspectives on Viet Nam brought together some 40 scholars, theologians, writers and intellectuals from Asia, Europe, Africa, and the United States. The work of the Conference, according to its press release, was based on "the assumption that Cold War conceptions and policies derived from them have failed and have produced the disaster which Viet Nam is today. Therefore, the Conference sought alternative conceptions which might result in reasonable and constructive policies to achieve a peaceful and humane end to the war in Viet Nam."
The Conference divided into four Study Groups, each considering the problem of peace in Viet Nam from different aspects. One group considered the situation from the standpoint of international politics; the second, in terms of social and economic development; the third, in terms of conflict and conflict resolution; the fourth, from the standpoint of revolutionary warfare.
Although the Study Groups worked independently and developed a variety of recommendations, there was agreement among the participants on the following propositions Again quoting from the press report of the conference
"that the bombing of North Viet Nam must cease
that there should be a general cease fire in South Viet Nam
that the settlement of the problem of Viet Nam must be considered as political, not military
that negotiations must include the National Liberation Front in its own right as a principal party to the conflict in South Viet Nam
that peace and stability in Asia require the admission of the People's Republic of China to the United Nations
that there should be a fundamental reassessment of the goals and methods of United States foreign policy."
The record group consists of two series, Conference Papers and Sound recordings of the speeches and study group sessions at the conference. The papers series includes correspondence, minutes, papers read at the conference, and other administrative files. Correspondents (to and from) include:
Hannah Arendt, Sept. 17, 1965
Germaine Brée, Aug. 3, 1965, Aug. 9, 1965, Sept. 25, 1965, Oct. 11, 1965
J. Daniel Burke
J. Edgar Edwards
Jerome D. Frank, Sept. 9, 1965
Erich Fromm, Sept. 4, 1965
Herbert Kelman
Martin Luther King, Jr., Aug. 26, 1965, Aug. 31, 1965, Sept. 8, 1965, Sept. 17, 1965
Archibald MacLeish, Aug. 5, 1965, Aug. 13, 1965
Emil Mazey, Aug. 30, 1965, Sept. 7, 1965
Arthur Miller, Aug. 27, 1965, Sept. 30, 1965
Mary C. Wright, June 7, 1965, July 28, 1965, Sept. 5, 1965.
The sound recordings include speeches by Arthur Miller, Edwin T. Dahlberg, Lord Fenner Brockway, Makoto Oda, and Emil Mazey, among others.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Congresses.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Women and peace.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Intellectual life.; University of Michigan--Congresses.; Edwards, J. Edgar (Joseph Edgar), 1909-1973.
Contributors - Sound Recordings:
Kelman, Herbert C.; Mazey, Emil, 1913-1983; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005.
Contributors - Papers:
Arendt, Hannah.; Brée, Germaine.; Burke, Joseph Daniel.; Edwards, J. Edgar (Joseph Edgar), 1909-1973.; Frank, Jerome D. (Jerome David), 1909-2005.; Fromm, Erich, 1900-1980.; Kelman, Herbert C.; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968.; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982.; Mazey, Emil, 1913-1983; Miller, Arthur, 1915-2005.; Wright, Mary Clabaugh.
Genre Terms:
Sound recordings.
- Conference papers 1965
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Papers 1965 read at the conference, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Prospectus (Box 1)
  - Minutes 1965 (Box 1)
  - Reports 1965 (Box 1)
  - Schedules 1965 (Box 1)
  - Clippings and press releases 1965 (Box 1)
  - Lists 1965 (Box 1)
- Sound recordings: reel-to-reel tapes
  - Plenary session: Welcomes and keynote addresses September 14, 1965, 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)
    (tape no. 1)
  - Study Group #2 September 14, 1965 p.m. session, 1 hour 13 minutes; 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)
    (tape no. 2, track no. 1)
  - Study Group #2 September 14, 1965 p.m. session, 1 hour 18 minutes; 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)
    (tape no. 2, track no. 2)
  - Study Group #2 September 15, 1965 a.m. session, 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)
    (tape no. 3, track no. 1)
  - Study Group #2 September 15, 1965 a.m. session, 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)
    (tape no. 3, track no. 2)
  - Study Group #2 September 15, 1965 p.m. session, 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)
    (tape no. 4, track no. 1)
  - Study Group #2 September 15, 1965 p.m. session, 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)
    (tape no. 4, track no. 2)
  - Study Group #2, a.m., Study Group 2 September 16, 1965 p.m. session, 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)
    (tape no. 5, track no. 1)
  - Study Group #2 September 16, 1965 p.m. session, 3 3/4 ips (Box 1)
    (tape no. 5, track no. 2)
  - September 17, 1965 sessions, 7 1/2 ips
    (tape no. 6)
    - DeWitt Baldwin speech (Box 1)
    - Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. letter is read (Box 1)
    - Daniel Burke, moderator, reads Joint Statement (Box 1)
    - Report of Study Group #1 (Box 1)
    - Study Group #2 -- Douglas F. Dowd (Box 1)
  - September 17, 1965 sessions, 7 1/2 ips
    (tape no. 7)
    - Study Group 2 -- Douglas F. Dowd (Box 1)
    - Study Group 3 -- Morton Deutsch (Box 1)
    - Study Group 4 -- Eqbal Ahmad (Box 1)
  - September 17, 1965 sessions, 7 1/2 ips
    (tape no. 8)
    - Study Group 4-Eqbal Ahmad (Box 1)
    - Study Group 4-Jean Lacouture (Box 1)
    - Ahmad gives brief translation of Lacouture presentation (Box 1)
  - September 17, 1965 sessions, 7 1/2 ips
    (tape no. 9)
    - Daniel Burke announcements (Box 1)
    - Albert Chammah introduces Ernst Winter, speech (Box 1)
    - Mohammed Lahbabi, speech (Box 1)
  - September 17, 1965 sessions, 7 1/2 ips
    (tape no. 10)
    - Mohammed Lahbabi speech (cont.) (Box 1)
    - Edwin T. Dahlberg, speech (Box 1)
  - September 17, 1965 sessions, 7 1/2 ips
    (tape no. 11)
    - Edwin T. Dahlberg, speech (cont.) (Box 1)
    - Robert Parris, speech (Box 1)
    - Daniel Burke adjourns the afternoon session (Box 1)
  - September 17, 1965 sessions, 7 1/2 ips
    (tape no. 12)
    - Marshall D. Sahlins introduction (Box 1)
    - Lord Fenner Brockway speech (Box 1)
  - September 17, 1965 sessions, 7 1/2 ips
    (tape no. 13)
    - Marshall D. Sahlins introduction (Box 1)
    - Makoto Oda speech (Box 1)
  - September 17, 1965 sessions, 7 1/2 ips
    (tape no. 14)
    - Makoto Oda, speech (cont.) (Box 1)
    - Marshall D. Sahlins introduction (Box 1)
    - Emil Mazey speech (Box 1)
    - Arthur Miller speech (Box 1)
  - September 17, 1965 sessions, 7 1/2 ips
    (tape no. 15)
    - Arthur Miller speech (cont.) (Box 1)
    - Marshall D. Sahlins adjourns session (Box 1)